Guide to the Larry Silver Photograph Collection 1949-1989 PR 306
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Larry Silver Photograph Collection
1949-1989
PR 306
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
0.5 Linear feet
The Larry Silver Photograph Collection consists of 58 gelatin silver prints of New York City, mainly Manhattan and the Bronx, taken between 1949 and 1989. The majority of the photographs are from the early 1950s.
Scope and Contents Note
The Larry Silver Photograph Collection consists of 58 gelatin silver prints taken from 1949-1989, mostly in Manhattan and the Bronx. The photographs capture scenes of everyday life in New York City, particularly during the post-World War II era of the early 1950s. Images include a street carnival; an argument on the subway between two elderly women; a woman swimming in the East River; a camp for children with polio; people waiting for a train at Grand Central Terminal; and laundry hanging out on a clothesline strung between apartment buildings.
Children feature prominently in many photographs: two boys playing on a construction site; kids having a snowball fight; children peering into a toy shop window; a boy with crutches climbing to the top of a slide. Notable landmarks include the Empire State Building, the original Pennsylvania Station before it was demolished, and the United Nations building when it was a new addition to the city’s skyline; as well as iconic locations such as the subway, the river piers, Central Park, and New York Botanical Gardens.
Provenance
Gift of William and Jeryl Silverstein, 2014
Biographical Note
Larry Silver was born in the Bronx in 1934. He began photographing as a student at the High School of Industrial Art in Manhattan, and his early photography focused on the urban environment around him. Mentored by Lou Bernstein and other Photo League photographers, Silver's work won him a scholarship to the Art Center School in Los Angeles. There he documented the culture of body builders at Muscle Beach in Santa Monica.
Silver returned to the East Coast in 1959, and opened a photography studio in New York City. His photographs have apppeared in numerous publications, including Forbes, Life, and Time. Larry Silver’s work is included in the collections of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, the Whitney Museum of American Art, the Smithsonian, and the Brooklyn Museum, among others.
His work has been published in numerous books and catalogues including Made in California (2000); New York, Portrait of a City (2010); This Was the Photo League (2001) and Suburban Visions (2002).
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to 20 exposures of stable, unbound material per day. See guidelines in Print Room for details.
- [1] Grand Central Terminal, 1952 (Box 1)
- [2] Macy's Parade, 1951 (Box 1)
- [3] Bronx River Dock, 1951 (Box 1)
- [4] Children Playing, 1952 (Box 1)
- [5] Boy on United Nations Construction Pile, 1951 (Box 1)
- [6] Bronx Subway Station, 1950 (Box 1)
- [7] Penn Station Lower Level, 1951 (Box 1)
- [8] Times Square, 1951 (Box 1)
- [9] Penn Station, 1951 (Box 1)
- [10] Subway Rider, 1950 (Box 1)
- [11] Bronx Street Scene, 1949 (Box 1)
- [12] Seated Man in Manhattan Supermarket, 1952 (Box 1)
- [13] Polio Camp, 1952 (Box 1)
- [14] Manhattan Backyard, 1952 (Box 1)
- [15] Nearby Eggs, 1952 (Box 1)
- [16] Dog at Store Window, 1952 (Box 1)
- [17] 34th Street, 1952 (Box 1)
- [18] Subway Scene, 1950 (Box 1)
- [19] Street Carnival, 1950 (Box 1)
- [20] Gas Station Attendant, 1955 (Box 1)
- [21] Boy with Sled, 1950 (Box 1)
- [22] Grand Central Terminal, 1952 (Box 1)
- [23] Toy Store Window, 1950 (Box 1)
- [24] Leaving Penn Station, 1952 (Box 1)
- [25] Couple in Central Park (same as 52), 1950 (Box 1)
- [26] Library Steps, 1950 (Box 1)
- [27] Woman Entering Subway, 1950 (Box 1)
- [28] Gun Duel, 1953 (Box 1)
- [29] Woman at Window, 1950 (Box 1)
- [30] Raft, Bronx Botanical Gardens, 1950 (Box 1)
- [31] Man Walking in Snow Storm, 1989 (Box 1)
- [32] Snowball Fight, 1952 (Box 1)
- [33] Sidewalk Scene, 1959 (Box 1)
- [34] Subway Staircase, 1950 (Box 1)
- [35] Woman and Baby Carriage, 1952 (Box 1)
- [36] At the Bronx Botanical Gardens, 1950 (Box 1)
- [37] Clubhouse, Manhattan, 1950 (Box 1)
- [38] Boy with Crutch Climbing Slide, 1950 (Box 1)
- [39] Automat, 1950 (Box 1)
- [40] Child and Elevated Train, 1951 (Box 1)
- [41] Central Park, 1953 (Box 1)
- [42] Boy on Staten Island Ferry (Box 1)
- [43] Child and Pet (Box 1)
- [44] Sleeping Man on Subway, 1950 (Box 1)
- [45] Boy on Rooftop, 1951 (Box 1)
- [46] Boy Swimming in East River, 1953 (Box 1)
- [47] Boy with Polio on Ramp, 1952 (Box 1)
- [48] Closed at Grand Central Terminal, 1983 (Box 1)
- [49] Bronx Subway Staircase, 1951 (Box 1)
- [50] Under the El, 1951 (Box 1)
- [51] Lower Level Staircase, 1951 (Box 1)
- [52] Couple in Central Park (same as 25), 1950 (Box 1)
- [53] Homeless Women Quarreling on Subway, 1951 (Box 1)
- [54] Children on United Nations Construction Pile (same as 56), 1951 (Box 1)
- [55] Boy on Saw Horse, 1950 (Box 1)
- [56] Children on United Nations Construction Pile (same as 54), 1951 (Box 1)
- [57] Woman Swimming in East River, 1950 (Box 1)
- [58] Harold and Gloria Before the Prom, Bronx, 1952 (Box 1)